<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Ecology and Evolution Unit</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2015-08-25T12:45:20-04:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Eco Evo Lab</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>ecoevo@oist.jp</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dorothy gets A+ for her thesis]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/dorothy-gets-a-for-her-thesis/" />
  <id>/dorothy-gets-a-for-her-thesis</id>
  <published>2015-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Our last spring’s intern Dorothy Immaculate has graduated from university, and received an A+ for the thesis that she did in our lab. Excellnt job Dorothy, and, Carmen, who was the one actually reposible for thesis supervision!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dorothy-gets-a-for-her-thesis/&quot;&gt;Dorothy gets A+ for her thesis&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on August 25, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Collecting bees in Arizona]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/collecting-bees-in-arizona/" />
  <id>/collecting-bees-in-arizona</id>
  <published>2015-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past couple of years we’ve been looking at how populations of European honeybees (&lt;em&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/em&gt;) evolve in response to emergent diseases, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms8991&quot;&gt;focusing primarily on a population near Ithaca, NY&lt;/a&gt;. It seems that the Ithaca population evolved in relative isolation, but elsewhere in the range of the bees in the United States, the arrival of the parasitic mite &lt;em&gt;Varroa destructor&lt;/em&gt; also led to extensive gene flow from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Africanized_bee&quot;&gt;Africanized bees&lt;/a&gt;. Although bees from Africa were first introduced to Brazil in the 1950, they arrived in the Southern U.S. in the early 1990s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b2/Killerbees_ani.gif&quot; alt=&quot;African spread&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This arrival took place at the same time that &lt;em&gt;Varroa&lt;/em&gt; swept through the US, causing large-scale introgression of African genes into the previously European populations. This is likely due to the fact that African bees are inherently more &lt;em&gt;Varroa&lt;/em&gt;-resistant than European bees, and are also better adapted to hot weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1449774/bin/5030f4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above figure from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1449774/&quot;&gt;Pinto &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2005 &lt;/a&gt; shows how in one population in Texas, after the arrival of mites in the early 1990s (they were first detected in 1995), the proportion of African mitochondrial DNA has increased rapidly. Such introgression seems to have been ubiquitous throughout the Southern United States. But what genes have driven it? This question is of great importance for beekeeping around the world, since European honeybee colonies have to be treated for &lt;em&gt;Varroa&lt;/em&gt; several times a year, so that they will survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, we’ve already obtained samples of wild honeybees from Texas and Arizona from before the arrival of &lt;em&gt;Varroa&lt;/em&gt;, and shortly after its arrival. We would like to compare them with the bees that live there now, in the presence of the mites, to try identify which genes may be involved in resistance. So, this means we had to get some bees from near Tucson, a population that has been studies for many decades (we also have a population from Texas, but that’s another story). In the desert, where there are no trees, bees nest in rock crevices and you can sometimes even see the comb sticking out. Thanks to Gerry Loper, who has worked for the USDA bee lab for many decades, and still visits his bee populations, we were able to locate 40 colonies in the course of just a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/arizona-collecting-bees.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Africanized bees are not friendly, and can pursue you for hundreds of meters if you get them really mad, so a bee suit is necessary for this sort of work, though it gets a bit hot in the Arizona desert sun (temperatures in the high 30s). We had to start our days at 6am, at sunrise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a great trip, and I am really grateful to Gloria Degrandi-Hoffman and USDA Carl Hayden Bee Research Center for hooking me up with a field vehicle and two excellent techs, as well as for giving me a opportunity to give a talk about my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/arizona-collecting-team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt; Mona, Henry and Gerry.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/collecting-bees-in-arizona/&quot;&gt;Collecting bees in Arizona&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on August 20, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't tread on me: How well do we really understand stingray venom?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/dont-tread-on-me-how-well-do-we-really-understand-stingray-venom/" />
  <id>/dont-tread-on-me-how-well-do-we-really-understand-stingray-venom</id>
  <published>2015-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Steve Aird</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Wading in slow-moving, shallow water on a beach along a tropical river sounds like an idyllic vacation, but last summer, for Brazilian Kalley Ferreira, doing so turned into an unbelievable nightmare. He felt something move under the sand beneath his feet, but before he could react, that unseen something stabbed him in the arch of his left foot. Despite indescribable pain, he still managed to get a good look at the perpetrator, an adult freshwater stingray more than 60 cm wide, flapping silently away. Because he is a physician, Kalley wrote the most detailed case history to date and after prodding from his friend, toxinologist Nelson Jorge da Silva, Jr., he agreed to write a manuscript. Nelson, in turn called upon his colleague, OIST’s Steve Aird, and physician Raimundo Pinto to help. Nelson reviewed the stingray biological literature while Steve evaluated the toxicological and medical literature. Their combined efforts and Kalley’s case history will soon be published in the journal, Toxins. What they discovered came as something of a surprise. Many Brazilian emergency medical personnel have no idea how to treat freshwater stingray stings, largely because so little is known about stingray venoms. In fact, it is far from clear which of the envenomation sequelae arise from toxic substances produced by the stingrays (venom and mucus) and which come from the great variety of bacteria that inhabits the mucus covering the rays. By reading this brief paper and perusing the gory photos of Kalley’s foot, you can enjoy the trauma vicariously,… which is probably the best way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read this paper online for free in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/7/6/2272/html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toxins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dont-tread-on-me-how-well-do-we-really-understand-stingray-venom/&quot;&gt;Don&#39;t tread on me: How well do we really understand stingray venom?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on June 12, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Males are here to stay!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/press%20release/publication/evolutionary-constraints/" />
  <id>/press%20release/publication/evolutionary-constraints</id>
  <published>2015-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;There is a wide variety of reproductive strategies in the world, and how and why organisms a reproductive strategy remains a mystery. Our former postdoc Misato Miyakawa has spend a long time carefully rearing little fire ants (&lt;em&gt;Wasmannia auropunctata&lt;/em&gt;),  which come from populations where queen can reproduce either clonally or sexually. Although clonal reproduction seems to have a lot of advantages, clonal queens still mate with males, using their sperm to produce workers. However, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/hdy/journal/v105/n2/full/hdy2009169a.html&quot;&gt;previos research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that clonal queens have the genetic capacity to produce both queens and workers clonally. So why mate? We found that if the queens don’t mate, their fecundity is actually really low, suggesting that mating is necessary to enhance colony-level worker production. Curiously, this was also the case for queens from sexual populations, where few of the eggs laid by virgin queens survived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the OIST press release &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oist.jp/news-center/news/2015/4/16/evolution-puts-checks-virgin-births&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and find the actual paper on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs00114-015-1265-8&quot;&gt;Science of Nature web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/press%20release/publication/evolutionary-constraints/&quot;&gt;Males are here to stay!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on April 17, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evolution of division of labor]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ants/evolution-of-division-of-labor/" />
  <id>/ants/evolution-of-division-of-labor</id>
  <published>2015-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Ant worker traits are remarkable in that they evolve despite the fact that the workers themselves do not reproduce. As a part of our ongong collaboration with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sites.sas.upenn.edu/linksvayer-lab&quot;&gt;Linksvayer Lab&lt;/a&gt;, in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://elifesciences.org/content/4/e04775?_ga=1.25883067.769126097.1432248984&quot;&gt;recently published paper in eLife&lt;/a&gt; we showed that the evolution of genes involved in social behavior is constrained by the effects of gene co-expression networks. You can listen to a podcast where Tim Linksvayer describes this work &lt;a href=&quot;http://elifesciences.org/podcast/episode18&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ants/evolution-of-division-of-labor/&quot;&gt;Evolution of division of labor&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on March 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSPE: Genomics of Social Parasite Evolution Workshop]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/gspe-genomics-of-social-parasite-evolution-workshop/" />
  <id>/gspe-genomics-of-social-parasite-evolution-workshop</id>
  <published>2014-10-23T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-23T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We were happy to host our excellent US and European-based collaborators to jointly work on the evolution of social parasite genomes. In the few days of the workshop we made major progress, finally bringing the project over the hill and hopefully en route to eventual publication.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;../images/GSPE.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;../images/GSPE.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Participants (as ordered in photo): Ti Eriksson (Arizona State University), Sara Helms Cahan (University of Vermont), Karsten Kemena (Muenster University), Andy Suarez (University of Illinois), Sasha Mikheyev (OIST) Misato Miyakawa (OIST), Juergen Gadau (ASU), Chris Smith (Earlham College), Martin Helmkampf (ASU). &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/gspe-genomics-of-social-parasite-evolution-workshop/&quot;&gt;GSPE: Genomics of Social Parasite Evolution Workshop&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on October 23, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Snake photography at the Okinawa Prefectural Institute of Health and Environment]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/snake-photography-at-the-okinawa-prefectural-institute-of-health-and-environment/" />
  <id>/snake-photography-at-the-okinawa-prefectural-institute-of-health-and-environment</id>
  <published>2014-09-01T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-01T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Steve and I went to photograph some of the snakes kept at the Okinawa Prefectural Institute of Health and Environment in the care of our long-time collaborator Terada-san. To get a sense of what the snakes look like, you can see my photographs &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/photos/118288632229735393241/albums/6054082162370620497&quot; title=&quot;here&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The first two individuals are &lt;em&gt;Protobothrops flavoviridis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. elegans&lt;/em&gt;, the Okinawa and Sakishima habus, respectively. The third individual is their hybrid that occurs in Okinawa. Note that it its shape is more similar to Okinawa habu, but its pigmentation, and particularly eye color is more similar to the Sakishima habu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sakishima habu is the one you most often see in Awamori containers; it is smaller than the Okinawa habu, being about half the size, and, I presume, is easier to stuff into a jar. They have escaped and have been spreading through parts of Okinawa, hybridizing with the native speces.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/snake-photography-at-the-okinawa-prefectural-institute-of-health-and-environment/&quot;&gt;Snake photography at the Okinawa Prefectural Institute of Health and Environment&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on September 01, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Degenerate adaptor sequences for detecting PCR duplicates in reduced representation sequencing data improve genotype-calling accuracy&#8221; paper published!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/degenerate-adaptor-sequences-for-detecting-pcr-duplicates-in-reduced-representation-sequencing-data-improve-genotype-calling-accuracy-paper-published/" />
  <id>/degenerate-adaptor-sequences-for-detecting-pcr-duplicates-in-reduced-representation-sequencing-data-improve-genotype-calling-accuracy-paper-published</id>
  <published>2014-08-27T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-08-27T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Together with our collaborators from the National University of Singapore we just published a &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1755-0998.12314/abstract&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; describing an improved method for making double-digest RAD-tag libraries. By adding a small run of degenerate nucleotides to the end of one of the Illumina indexes, you can barcode each individual ligation reaction and determine how many molecules participate in each reaction. This is a simple modification, that allows us to confidently make RAD-tag libraries using just a few nanograms of input material. The actual library preparation is not different — in this paper we describe a protocol that we use to process thousands of samples using a liquid handling robot, making 96 libraries at once.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/degenerate-adaptor-sequences-for-detecting-pcr-duplicates-in-reduced-representation-sequencing-data-improve-genotype-calling-accuracy-paper-published/&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Degenerate adaptor sequences for detecting PCR duplicates in reduced representation sequencing data improve genotype-calling accuracy&amp;#8221; paper published!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on August 27, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shikha scores at the top of her class]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/shikha-scores-at-the-top-of-her-class/" />
  <id>/shikha-scores-at-the-top-of-her-class</id>
  <published>2014-08-25T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-08-25T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Shikha just received her grades, scoring at the top of her class, and completing her thesis. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/shikha-scores-at-the-top-of-her-class/&quot;&gt;Shikha scores at the top of her class&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on August 25, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[It belongs in a museum!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/museum/" />
  <id>/museum</id>
  <published>2014-05-22T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-22T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Over lunch during one of his visits to OIST, my former boss Sydney Brenner suggested that I try a ribo-tailing technique for attaching adaptors to short DNA molecules. The idea is that the action of terminal transferase on riboguanidines creates a 3′ tail of controlled length, which can be used for attaching adaptors and synthesizing a second strand (&lt;a href=&quot;http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;amp;pmid=9512556&quot;&gt;Komura and Riggs, 1998&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003269705007979&quot;&gt;Lee and Weeks, 2006&lt;/a&gt;).We tried it, and it was amazing. This approach eventually produced a method that we use for working with degraded DNA, just published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0096793&quot;&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/a&gt; (and available in detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1GW4TzTCJAm8bjqOSC9-fmNRVPbS-3Ij5-2tSLYZygJM&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The PLoS ONE paper outlines this approach, at least an earlier version, and presents a fairly non-destructive way of extracting DNA form museum insects. Using this approach we could sequence RAD-tags from tiny 100 year old ants, and create a Hawaiian fruit fly phylogeny.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/museum/&quot;&gt;It belongs in a museum!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on May 22, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jatin visits Mikheyev&#8217;s unit as Research Intern]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/lab/news/jatin-visits-mikheyevs-unit-as-research-intern/" />
  <id>/lab/news/jatin-visits-mikheyevs-unit-as-research-intern</id>
  <published>2014-04-26T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-04-26T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jatin Aora</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I am Jatin Arora. I came to know about Prof. Alexander Mikheyev and his Ecology and Evolution unit at OIST in October, 2013. I was intrigued about the potential offered by using non-model systems, e.g. the species of honey bees, ants, snakes etc. to understand how organisms interact with their environment. In debut, I worked at distance with him on topic of Resilience to diseases in feral honey bee genome in third semester of my master studies at University Pierre and Marie Curie, Paris. Later, I joined the laboratory as research intern to do my master thesis. &lt;br /&gt;In present, I am working on the Introgressive hybridization of African genes into population of feral European bees. During my stay here, I hope to work in other areas as well, as the research in the laboratory is being done on a range of topics. The laboratory has cutting edge infrastructure. It is equipped with latest sequencing facilities. The experimental and analysis works are done in parallel which facilitates the access to data and validation of hypothesis. Along with working on computational analysis, I participate in wet lab experiments as well, which complements my learning. There are six nationalities in the laboratory which allows learning different cultures under one roof and makes the work environment more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lab/news/jatin-visits-mikheyevs-unit-as-research-intern/&quot;&gt;Jatin visits Mikheyev&amp;#8217;s unit as Research Intern&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on April 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[OIST-NTU Invasive Ant Symposium]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/oist-ntu-invasive-ant-symposium/" />
  <id>/oist-ntu-invasive-ant-symposium</id>
  <published>2014-04-01T06:42:49-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-04-01T06:42:49-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;../wp-content/uploads/2014/04/DSC0067.jpg&quot; class=&quot;grouped_elements&quot; rel=&quot;tc-fancybox-group1106&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-full wp-image-1107&quot; alt=&quot;NTU Group Visit&quot; src=&quot;../wp-content/uploads/2014/04/DSC0067.jpg&quot; width=&quot;580&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;NTU Group Visit&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were the proud hosts of Dr. Scotty Yang’s research group and his colleagues from Taiwan National University. His research group specializes in studying the patterns of  dispersal in a variety of invasive ant species. We were treated to a wide range of topics, including a few fascinating finding about Wolbachia distributions in invasive ants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taiwan talks&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global invasion history and Wolbachia infection patterns of crazy ant &lt;em&gt;Paratrechina longicornis&lt;/em&gt; I (Dr. Chin-Cheng Yang)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global invasion history and Wolbachia infection patterns of crazy ant &lt;em&gt;Paratrechina longicornis&lt;/em&gt; II (Ms. Shu-Ping Tseng)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global invasion history and Wolbachia infection patterns of yellow crazy ant &lt;em&gt;Anoplolepis gracilipes&lt;/em&gt; (Ms. Ho Han-Chih)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chemical ecology and seed collecting behaviors of invasive fire ants in Taiwan (Dr. Li-Chuan Lai)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OIST talks&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sex determination in &lt;em&gt;Vollenhovia emeryi&lt;/em&gt; (Dr. Misato Okamoto)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Molecular signatures of ancient mutualistic coevolution in attine ants and their fungal cultivars (Dr. Alexander Mikheyev)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/oist-ntu-invasive-ant-symposium/&quot;&gt;OIST-NTU Invasive Ant Symposium&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on April 01, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shikha Visits Mikheyev Unit]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/shikha-visits-mikheyev-unit/" />
  <id>/shikha-visits-mikheyev-unit</id>
  <published>2014-01-10T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2014-01-10T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Shikha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
I am from Delhi, the capital city of  India. Born and brought up in the second most crowded metropolis city in India, I always yearned to be close to nature. I completed my graduation in Biological Sciences from Sri Venkateswara College, Delhi University. I am currently enrolled in the Masters course on Biodiversity and Conservation at Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University, New Delhi.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joined Prof. Alexander Mikheyev lab in January 2014 as a research intern. I will be working here for five months on a transcriptomes and proteomes study of snake venom (pitvipers). These include the Okinawan native species &lt;i&gt;Protobothrops flavoviridis &lt;/i&gt;(Okinawa habu) and &lt;i&gt;Ovophis okinavensis&lt;/i&gt; (Himehabu) and hybridized species due to human activities &lt;i&gt;P. elegans&lt;/i&gt; (Sakishima habu) and &lt;i&gt;P. mucrosquamatus&lt;/i&gt; (Taiwanese habu). A previous study (Aird et. al. 2013) used both Illumina cDNA sequencing and mass spectrometry to compare the transcriptomes and proteomes of native pitvipers. We will be doing cDNA sequencing combined with MS profiling. This will help in quantitative comparison of snake venom composition. This unit will definitely help to enhance my knowledge and working skills. This will be a strong foundation for building my future and boosting my career in research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;../images/shikha.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;../images/shikha.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have also worked on different projects in my home country. My past projects involved the molecular taxonomy of selected camel spiders (Arachnida : Solifugae) of India as well as a web designing project on Indian tribes and their role in biodiversity conservation. I have also worked on screening of genes involved in retinal dystrophies in Indian patients at L.V Prasad Eye Institute. My other interests include photography, sports, reading, exploring nature and arts and crafts.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/shikha-visits-mikheyev-unit/&quot;&gt;Shikha Visits Mikheyev Unit&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on January 10, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Habu study press release by OIST!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/habu-study-press-release-by-oist/" />
  <id>/habu-study-press-release-by-oist</id>
  <published>2013-12-10T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-12-10T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to read the take home message of the habu study without wading through the paper, the kind folks at OIST’s Communications have drawn up a handy press release. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oist.jp/news-center/news/2013/12/9/biting-snake-venom-mysteries&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/habu-study-press-release-by-oist/&quot;&gt;Habu study press release by OIST!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on December 10, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nichole Bennett visiting Mikheyev Unit]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/nichole-bennett-visiting-mikheyev-unit/" />
  <id>/nichole-bennett-visiting-mikheyev-unit</id>
  <published>2013-11-29T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-11-29T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nichole Bennett</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
Nichole Bennett is a Ph.D. candidate and National Science Graduate Research Fellow in Ecology, Evolution, and Behavior at The University of Texas at Austin, where she studies climate change impacts by investigating local adaptation and thermal biology in a butterfly-plant system. She will be working with the Mikheyev Unit for six months to look at genome-wide patterns of host-associated differentiation in two species of butterflies (*Euphydryas editha *and *E. aurinia*).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
Populations of the butterfly *E. editha* exhibit spatial variation in diet, and populations differ in a suite of highly heritable, complex traits. A related species, *E. aurinia* also demonstrates a geographic mosaic of host plant use but much smaller differences in its adaptations to different plant species. A previous study ([Mikheyev *et al.* 2013][1]) used AFLP and microsatellite markers to search for host-associated genomic differences in the two species. Somewhat paradoxically, the butterfly with weaker phenotypic differences (*E. aurinia*) had stronger differentiation than the butterfly with stronger differences in adaptation (*E. editha*). Nichole’s work at OIST with Dr. Mikheyev will follow up on this work by using higher-resolution next generation sequencing methods to look for differences in the two species in the level of host-associated differentiation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;../images/nichole_bennett.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;../images/nichole_bennett.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In addition to her research interests, Nichole is also involved in science education and communication. During fall semesters, she organizes a weekly informal [Introduction to Biological Statistics Course][2]. She also hosts a weekly science radio show [They Blinded Me With Science][3] on 91.7FM KVRX Austin and coordinates [Science Under the Stars][4], a free, outdoor lecture series that helps graduate students communicate their research to the public.
&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nichole-bennett-visiting-mikheyev-unit/&quot;&gt;Nichole Bennett visiting Mikheyev Unit&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on November 29, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goodbye Invitrogen ripoff product]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/goodbye-invitrogen-ripoff-product/" />
  <id>/goodbye-invitrogen-ripoff-product</id>
  <published>2013-11-27T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-11-27T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;With the help of Ken Meacham of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.oist.jp/ciu/mahesh-m-bandi&quot;&gt;Bandi Unit&lt;/a&gt;, we have successfully used some magnets to inexpensively 3D print our own magnetic stands based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:79424&quot;&gt;this design&lt;/a&gt; and some inexpensive &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kjmagnetics.com/proddetail.asp?prod=B824&quot;&gt;magnets&lt;/a&gt;. They look like cheap imitations, but just as well, if not better, and cost orders of magnitude less (last I checked the commercial stand in the background would set you back a cool &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lifetechnologies.com/order/catalog/product/12321D&quot;&gt;US$531&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;../images/home-made-rack.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;../images/home-made-rack.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	 
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goodbye-invitrogen-ripoff-product/&quot;&gt;Goodbye Invitrogen ripoff product&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on November 27, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quantitative proteomics of snake venoms paper published]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/quantitative-proteomics-of-snake-venoms-paper-published/" />
  <id>/quantitative-proteomics-of-snake-venoms-paper-published</id>
  <published>2013-11-14T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-11-14T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to the hard work of Steve, and the help of Alex and Roy in mass spec, we were able to quantitatively measure protein concentrations in the venoms of two local snake species. The paper just went online in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/14/790/abstract&quot;&gt;BMC Genomics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/quantitative-proteomics-of-snake-venoms-paper-published/&quot;&gt;Quantitative proteomics of snake venoms paper published&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on November 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Host-associated genomic differentiation paper recommended by F1000]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/host-associated-genomic-differentiation-paper-recommended-by-f1000/" />
  <id>/host-associated-genomic-differentiation-paper-recommended-by-f1000</id>
  <published>2013-11-06T05:42:49-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-11-06T05:42:49-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sasha</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>alexander.mikheyev@oist.jp</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It was a long, hard road, but our &lt;a href=&quot;http://ecoevo.unit.oist.jp/lab/?attachment_id=1027&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; is getting some recognition! F1000′s Dr. Ian Wang &lt;a href=&quot;http://f1000.com/prime/718063447&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; that “this finding highlights the importance of considering multiple factors, including dispersal, population sizes, spatial variation in ecologically-important traits, and population histories, for understanding how ecological adaptation contributes to patterns of differentiation throughout the genome.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope we the next phase of the study, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mikheyev/euphies&quot;&gt;taking it next-generation&lt;/a&gt; is as successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://f1000.com/prime/718063447?bd=1&amp;amp;ui=30390&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img id=&quot;bg&quot; alt=&quot;Access the recommendation on F1000Prime&quot; src=&quot;http://cdn.f1000.com.s3.amazonaws.com/images/badges/badgef1000.gif&quot; class=&quot;grouped_elements&quot; rel=&quot;tc-fancybox-group1026&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/host-associated-genomic-differentiation-paper-recommended-by-f1000/&quot;&gt;Host-associated genomic differentiation paper recommended by F1000&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eco Evo Lab at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Unit&lt;/a&gt; on November 06, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
